<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Braj_Mandal</string>
    <string name="banke_bihari"> The image of Bihariji installed in the Shri Banke Bihari Mandir, is the one granted to Swami Haridas by the celestial couple Shyama-Shyam themselves. Submitting to the desire of devotees The Lord appeared in person with his divine consort and left back a black charming image before disappering.

Swami Haridas ji was born to Shri Ashudhir and his wife Smt Gangadevi on the day of Radha Ashtami i.e. eighth day of second (bright) fortnight of Bhadrapad month of the year 1535 Vikrami(1478 A.D.). He was born in a small village, now known as Haridaspur, near Aligarh in Uttar Pradesh. The linage of the family can be traced back to Shri Gargacharya. Shri Gargachrya was the kulguru (family guru) of Yadavs and visited Brij secretly for conducting the Namkaran Samskar (naming ceremony) of young Krishna and Balram on request of Sri Vasudev. A branch of the family migrated to Multan (now in Pakistan), but some of them returned after a long time. Sri Ashudhir was one such migrant who after returning from Multan settled at the outskirts of Brij, near Aligarh.

Swami Haridas was the reincarnation of Lalita ‘sakhi’ (female friend), of the inner consortium of Lord Krishna. This easily explains the fact that even in his childhood, he was more into meditation and scriptures, while other children of his age were busy playing. He was married at the suitable age according to the time to Harimati. Even after his marriage, young Haridas stayed away from worldly pleasures and concentrated on meditation. Harimati ji was such a saintly soul herself that on realizing the inclination of her husband, she prayed intensely and was bodily transported to the heavenly abode of Lord by entering the flame of a small lamp in the presence of Haridas. No physical remains were left behind!

Soon after that Haridas left his village for Vrindavan, which was a dense forest at that time and choose a secluded spot, which is now known as Nidhivan, to practice his music and to enjoy eternal bliss of meditation. He constantly and continuously meditated on Nitya Ras and Nitya Bihar of Lord at Nitya Vrindavan. His way of Sadhna was to compose and sing songs in the praise of Lord. While on earth, living in a mortal state, he facilitated his regular unobstructed entry in the Nitya Bihar and always enjoyed the pleasure of closeness of Lord. He chose a secluded and densely forested area, Kunj, in Nidhivan as his gateway to the nirvana and was mostly sitting there, singing, meditating and surfing in the ocean of eternal bliss.

His disciples were curious about this place and one day with permission of Swamiji, they all entered the kunj. But instead of seeing anything they were almost blinded by bright, intense light, which seemed to fill the whole place. On knowing of their plight Swamiji himself went there, and then after his requests, lord appeared in person with his divine consort, pleasantly smiling and in a playful mood and casting a spell of charm on every living being present there. Those who witnessed this, were so spell bounded by the beauty of the Lord and his consort, that they couldn’t even blink their eyes, it seemed that all of them had turned into stone statues.

The legend as handed down to the generations of Goswamis, says that the beauty of the divine couple was such that no one wanted to loose the sight and proximity of divinity, but then what kind of divinity is it, which cannot make a mere mortal swoon and charmed enough to forget and give up the world and its luxuries? The beauty of the divine couple was so much that lesser mortals, like you and me, won’t be able to bear such a heavenly beauty. Sensing this Swami Haridasji requested both of them to take a single form, as the world won’t be able to bear their image. He requested them to take a single form like Ghan(cloud) and Damini(lightning) thus giving a perfect metaphor to the combined beauty of dark Lord and his fair consort, Radhaji.

Also he wanted his beloved lord to be in front of his eyes always. Granting him his both wishes, the couple turned itself into one single black charming idol, the same one that you see in the temple today. The charm and beauty of Shri Banke Bihariji is the only reason why the ‘darshan’ in the temple is never continuous but is broken by the curtain drawn on him regularly. It is also said that if one stares long enough into the eyes of Shri Banke Bihariji, the person would lose his self consciousness.

Thus came into existence the physical form of Lord Banke Bihari, popularly know as Bihariji. The responsibility of Sewa of Bihariji was handed over to Goswami Jagannath by Swamiji himself. Goswami Jagannath was one of the principal disciple and younger brother of Swamiji. By tradition, the Sewa is performed by descendents of Jagannath Goswami till day.

Initially the deity was installed in a temple close to the first appearance in Nidhivan. A new temple befitting the glory of Bihariji was constructed in 1862 AD. Goswamis themselves mobilized resources for the construction. The temple is an architectural beauty in itself and follows the contemporary Rajasthani style.

The sewa of the Bihariji is unique in its own way. It is performed in three parts every day ie Shringar, Rajbhog and Shayan. While shringar (which includes bath, dressing and adornment with jewellery like crown and necklaces) and Rajbhog(feast) is offered in the forenoon, Shayan Sewa (shayan means sleep) is offered in the evening. The temple doesn’t have a tradition of Mangala (early morning) sewa. Swami Haridas did not favour Mangla Sewa as he wanted his child like Lord to take complete rest and did not want to disturb him out of deep slumber so early in the morning.So, the temple today stands with its full glory, inside which the Lord himself resides. It is thronged by thousands of visitors everyday.
    </string>

    <string name="Barsana">
        Barsana is located about 50 km to the north-west of Mathura and 19 km towards the north-west direction of Govardhan. Barsana is the place where Sri Radharani, eternal beloved of Lord Krishna enjoyed her transcendental youth pastimes along with her friends and her parents. Barsana is also known as Vrishabhanupura after the name of its founder Vrishabhanu Maharaj, the father of Goddess Radha who used to live here along with his family. It is said that Nand Maharaj and Vrishabhanu Maharaj, both were good friends and when Nand Raeji shifted from Gokul due to the disturbances created by demons of Kansa, Vrishabhanu ji also shifted from Raval to Barsana. This is considered to be one of the Upvana of Vrindavan and embarks the gopi pastimes of Radharani and her friends.

According to the legendary epics of Varaha Puran and Padma Puran, once Brahmaji performed the severe austerities to please Lord Krishna and asked him for the benediction to serve him in a way so that the dust of the lotus feet of Lord Krishna and all his devotees should always be on his forehead. Pleased by his prayers, Lord Krishna blessed Brahmaji with a boon to become a hill in this sacred land of Barsana. Barsana city is settled around at the foot on the slope of a hill which is differentiated divided into two parts. The longer hill which is white in colour is the Brahma hill and the other one with black colour and slightly smaller is the Vishnu hill. The mountain has four peaks representing the four heads of Lord Brahma. The peak where the palace of Vrishabhanu is located is known as Vrishabhanugarh. The other peak known as Vilasgarh is located just across the edge of the Bhanugarh and is known for the loving transcendental pastimes of Radha and Krishna. Maangarh is an esoteric peak where Sri Radharani would go in isolation from Krishna in her loving anger state or Maan. Another peak where Lord Krishna along with his friends performed the pastime of collecting tax in the form of curd and butter from Gopis and Radharani has been named as Daangarh.

Apart from its spiritual importance Barsana also relishes its popularity due to the celebrations performed during Holi festival all over the world. During the festivities, firstly the Gopas (cowherd men) and the gopis (cowherd women) performs the ceremony at Sri Radharani temple and then plays holi in which Gopas try to throw color on gopis and they chase them with lathi (wooden staff). This form of holi celebration is called as lathmar holi. Barsana is also popular for its spirituality which is evident through its religious edifices dedicated primarily to Radharani.
    </string>

    <string name="Dwarkadhish">
        About The Place: The main draw for tourists coming to Dwarka, the Dwarkadhish Temple (Jagat Mandir), is believed to have been established more than 2500 years ago by Lord Krishna’s great grandson, Vajranabh. The ancient temple has been renovated several times, especially leaving imprints of 16th and 19th centuries. The temple stands on a small hill accessed by 50 plus steps, with heavily sculptured walls that cocoon the sanctum with the main Krishna idol. Around the complex lie other smaller shrines. The walls have intricately carved mythical characters and legends. The impressive 43 m high spire is topped with a flag made from 52 yards of cloth that flutters in the soft breeze from the Arabian Sea behind the temple. There are two doors (swarg and moksh) for the entry and exit of the temple. A bridge called Sudama Setu (7am–1pm, 4–7.30pm) at the base of the temple takes one across the Gomti creek towards the beach.

Brief History: Dwarka on the western tip of the Kathiawar Peninsula is clubbed with the holiest sites in India – the Char Dhams that include Badrinath, Puri and Rameshwaram. It is believed that Lord Krishna arrived here from Braj in Uttar Pradesh to build the city. The temple was established by his grandson. It is at the cusp of the Gomti River and the Arabian Sea, providing a scenic backdrop to the spiritual site. It is said that Dwarka was submerged under the sea six times and what we see now is its seventh avatar. The temple itself has a fascinating legend. The original structure was destroyed by Mahmud Begada in 1472, and subsequently rebuilt in the 15th-16th century. It was also feted by Adi Shankaracharya, the 8th century Hindu theologian and philosopher.
    </string>

<string name="Gita_Mandir">
    Gita Temple is a Hindu temple located in the Mathura district of Uttar Pradesh, India. This temple is also known as Birla Mandir. This temple is dedicated to Lord Vishnu. This temple is located on the Mathura Vrindavan Marg. The temple was built by Seth Jugal Kishore Birla, the owner of the Birla Group. In many states in India, Geeta Mandir and Birla Mandir have been built by Birla Group. This temple is one of them. Important shlokas and lesson of Srimad Bhagavad Gita have been written on the walls of this temple. The construction and environment of the temple is very beautiful.

There is also a Dharamshala for the travelers to rest in the temple premises. Devotees come from all over India to visit Lord Sri Krishna throughout the year. Special poojas are organized during Janmashtami festival and a large number of devotees attend this puja. During this time the temple is decorated with flowers and lights.
</string>

    <string name="Jaigurudev">
        Also known as Naam Yog Sadhna Mandir, Jaigurudev Mandir is dedicated to Baba Jai Gurudev, located on the National Highway 2, between Delhi and Agra. The celebrated man is a revered guruji among the devotees and he also runs a charitable organization and ashram. The temple hosts an annual Bhandaar festival which attracts hordes of pilgrims.

The temple is managed by the Jai Guru Dev Ashram and they do not charge anything from the public for entering. Visitors seeking peace and enlightenment from all over the country converge at this temple to worship Guru ji who is believed to lead them to the path of immortality. It is not just pilgrims and devotees who visit this temple. The architectural beauty of Jai Gurudev Temple attracts many architecture buffs as well, who gather to see the temple that resembles Taj Mahal. Built of white marbles, with domed structures and minarets in the temple complex, it is based on Hindu architecture.
    </string>

<string name="janmabhoom">
    Krishna is worshipped in hundreds of temples across the world. Some of them hold a special significance as they are associated with the life of the Lord and some others are important because of their historicity and the aura of spirituality associated with them. A few temples stand out conspicuously above other places of Krishna worship as they are directly associated with the events in the Lord’s life. They are generally located at Mathura, the place of Krishna’s birth, Vrindavana, where he spent most of his childhood days and Dwarka where he spent most of his adult life. Sri Krishna appeared over five thousand years ago in Mathura as the eighth child of Devaki and Vasudeva. Kansa was the king of Mathura and maternal uncle of lord Krishna .The place of His birth is known as Sri Krishna JanmaBhumi.

Numerous articles excavated from the site bear testimony to the legendary story of Sri Krishna’s birth. These artifacts are displayed in a museum near the main temple. One can find so many small shrines of other gods and goddess in the temple premises. This temple complex presents a magnificent and colossal structure that happens to be the most familiar place of Hindu adulation. Its popularity reflects in the long queue of the pilgrims who stands there for hours to have a holy darshan of their beloved lord. The birth place of Lord Krishna, “the best known, best loved and most complex of Lord Vishnu’s manifestations” – Mathura is today an important place of pilgrimage.

Studded with a number of ancient and modern temples, Mathura is the abode of God and divinity. Hinduism finds here a new dimension which is the colour of love with which Lord Krishna wanted to bind this entire world. The mild sound of devotees taking the hundred and eight names of Lord Krishna all day long covers the entire ambience of Mathura. The immense belief of the pilgrims coming here from different parts of the world is something that gives Mathura a well-deserved importance in the itinerary of Indian pilgrimages.

 Deity Worshipped

Lord Krishna is known by many different names in various traditions. The word Krishna means the person who is attractive to everyone. Historically, Sri Krishna appeared on the midnight of the 8th day of the dark half of the month of Sravana. This corresponds to July 19th 3228 BC. He exhibited His pastimes for a little over 125 years and disappeared on February 18th 3102 BC on the new moon night of Phalguna. (His departure marks the beginning of the current age of corruption known as Kali.)

It is true that Mathura is the holiest, and it is the only place in the universe where Brahma and Shakti have been manifested at the same place. It is in Mathura that Leelapurushottam Shri Krishna and Ashthabhuja Ma Yogmaya manifested.

The clearance of the birthplace of Lord Shri Krishna led to the recovery of many portions of a 1500-year-old temple, including the sanctum sanctorum (Garbha Griha) and a throne. The Medhi and sanctum sanctorum have been preserved. It is, indeed, the blessings of the Lord that when Emperor Aurangzeb demolished the temple and erected the Idgah on its plinth, the Idgah was actually constructed on the Sabha Mandap (prayer-hall) of the temple; the sanctum sanctorum, miraculously, remained intact and got buried under the debris. Resurrection of such an auspicious place has ensured that the devotees, once again, can enjoy the blessings of the Lord at His birthplace.

The magnificent and large Bhagavata Bhavan was constructed in honour of Shrimad Bhagavata. The Bhagavata Bhavan comprises, primarily, of five temples. The main temple is Radha-Krishna Yugal Sarkar, which draws the devotees and fills them with the sense of the divine presence of Shri Radha-Krishna. On the right is the temple of Shri Balram, Subhadra and Shri Jagannathji. On the left side is the temple of Shri Sita, Ram and Lakshmanji. In front of the temple of Shri Jagannathji, Shri Chaitanya Mahaprabhu is seen paying obeisance to the Lord beside the Garud-sthambh. In front of the temple of Shri Ram, Shri Hanumanji is seen standing, paying obeisance with folded hands. In front of Shri Chaitanya Mahaprabhu, we can have the darshan of Goddess Durga in her divine splendour. Shri Keshveshwar (Lord Shiva) is present here in the form of a mercury Linga.

The idols in these temples have special features. Those of Radha Krishna are of human size, nearly six feet high. The idols of Shri Jagannath, Subhadra and Balram have been made by the same sculptor who crafted the idols at Jagannath temple, Puri. Even the wood used is the same i.e. Nimba Kashtha.

Lord Keshveshwar is portrayed in his own mercurial Linga form, which has been solidified by mixing mercury with herbal extracts without the use of any metal alloy. This mercury Linga is, perhaps, the only one of its kind. Ancient scriptures say that those who pay obeisance to the mercurial Shiva Linga get their sins washed away. The darshan of the mercurial Shiva Linga is supposed to be as auspicious as darshan of the twelve Jyotirlingams. Lord Keshavdev, the ancient deity of the 12 Goswamis families. This deity has the icons of 24 avatāras of Lord Krishna (Vishnu) around Him.  One can see that only once a year, on Akṣaya Tṛtīya Day, when the Lord has His Chandan Yātra, and His entire body is smeared with sandalwood paste to cool Him in the summer heat. Originally Lord Keshavdev is one of the deities installed by Lord Krishna’s great-grandson after Lord Krishna departed this world.

Archeological facts

Megasthenes described Mathura as “a place of great regional importance” and suggested that it was then, as now, “a center of Krishna worship.” Christian Lassen noted that Megasthenes wrote of Krishna under the pseudonym of Heracles and that “Heracles”, or Krishna, was worshipped as God in the area through which the Yamuna River flows. A respected Indologist, Richard Garbe, agreed with Lassen’s analysis and called the testimony of Megasthenes indisputable. Soon, scholars like Alan Dahlquist, who had formerly supported the “borrowing theory,” changed their minds and admitted, in Dahlquist’s words, that Garbe had “exploded Weber’s theory once and for all.” The life of Krishna and the religion of Vaisnavism had not been influenced by Christianity, but had appeared autonomously on Indian soil and was already well-established by at least the third century BC.

The Mathura administration has found clinching evidence which proves the Hindus’ claim that the Shahi Mosque at Mathura was built over Shri Krishnajanmabhoomi temple. According to the locals, on August 14 the local administration started digging in the courtyard of the mosque for construction of some rooms for the security staff. During the digging process, the labourers found stone pillars, carving and an idol of a Hindu God. They immediately reported that matter to the authorities.

During the excavation work, various things were recovered that confirm this story. The articles that were recovered include utensils, some old figurines, and a rock platform that were commonly seen in the prisons of that period. These articles are displayed in a museum. Krishna Janmabhoomi Temple shares a common wall with a mosque, due to which there is heavy security in the temple. The present temple was built in the 20th century. A stone slab is present in the temple that symbolizes the original site where Lord Krishna was born.

Mathura is one of the most ancient towns of India and finds mention in the Ramayana, the oldest epic. This place was thickly forested and was known as Madhuvan then Madhupara and later on Mathura. Mathura became the capital of the Shursen republic in the 6th century BC and soon after was ruled by the Maurya Empire and the Sunga dynasty. Archaeological proof seems to point that, by 100 BC, Jains used to live in Mathura. The art form of Mathura and its culture reached its summit under the Kushan dynasty who had declared it as their capital. Many Buddhist relics have been found in the Mathura area. Many of which are found in the museums in Mathura, Calcutta and Lucknow.

History

Sri Krishna Janmabhoomi Temple was built over the prison which was believed to be the birth place of Lord Krishna. This temple was constructed five times. According to the epics and folklore of the area, the temple was first constructed about 5,000 years ago by the great-grandson of Lord Krishna, Vajranabha. Second time, the temple was built in 400 AD, during the reign of Chandragupta Vikramaditya, a Gupta Emperor. It was said that this temple was so beautiful that neither a painting nor a description could describe its grandeur. In 1017 AD, the temple was destroyed by Mahmud of Ghazni.

In 1150 AD, a person named Jajja constructed the temple for the third time during the reign of Raja Dhrupet Dev Janjua, Emperor of Mathura. Sri Caitanya Mahaprabhu (a Vaishnava saint) visited this temple in 16th Century. Later this temple was destroyed by Sikandar Lodi (Sultanate of Delhi) in the 16th Century.

About 125 years later, Raja Veer Singh Bundela of Orchha (or Urchha is a small town in Madhya Pradesh) constructed the Keshav Deo temple for the fourth time during the reign of Jahangir (Mughal Emperor). He built the temple with Rs 3.3 million. Again in 1669 AD, Aurangzeb destroyed this temple and built a mosque in its place known as Jami Masjid. He used the materials of the temple to construct the mosque.

In 1803, the city of Mathura came under the rule of British. In the year 1815, the East India Company auctioned the temple area. Raja Patnimal of Banaras bought the temple land to rebuild the temple. But his wish was not fulfilled. Later, Late Mahamana Pandit Madan Mohan Malaviya took the initiative to reconstruct the temple. He took financial assistance from Late Seth Jugal Kishoreji Birla. Jugal Kishoreji Birla established ‘Sri Krishna Janma Bhoomi Trust’ on 21st February, 1951. With the rigorous efforts of many people from 15th October, 1953, the construction of the temple was completed in February, 1982.

Scriptural references

The history and culture of this holy town revolve around the legends of Lord Krishna’s childhood. The great scholar Srila Vishvanatha Chakravarti neatly outlines Sri Krishna’s activities in this way: the first three years and four months were spent in Gokula, then equal lengths of time in Vmdavana and Nandagram, eighteen years and four months in Mathura, and finally ninety-six years and eight months in Dvaraka totalling 125 years of manifest pastimes.

As the legend goes, Mathura was founded in the Treta era by Shatrughna, the younger brother of Lord Rama and later was under the royalty of King Kamsa, the maternal uncle of Lord Krishna. According to Hindu mythology, Kamsa heard a divine prophecy saying that he would be killed by his sister Devki’s eighth son Krishna. Hence, he imprisoned Devaki and her husband Vasudeva and kept on killing their children one after another. But when Lord Krishna was born, miraculously all guards went to sleep, prison gates opened and Vasudeva carried his son to Gokul crossing the wild river Yamuna in the mid night. The divine prophecy came true and Krishna killed tyrant Kamsa and ruled Mathura for a long time. Vrindavan is the place where Lord Krishna spent his childhood leaving a number of myths and legends of love and friendship behind.

Cultural Significance

The beautiful city of Mathura lying on the banks of the great river Yamuna is considered to be one of the most ancient cities known to mankind. The history of Mathura dates back to 1600 B.C. going by the archaeologists. The city is considered to be the birth place of Lord Krishna according to Hindu mythology. The city is one of the most prominent places in the epic Mahabharata. It is known as the ‘Athens of ancient India’. The famous Greek traveler wrote about Mathura as the biggest kingdom rule by a small king in his book about his Indian odyssey ‘Indika’. He also described the people of Mathura as culturally rich and highly organized.

 According to Garuda Purana, Mathura along with Ayodhya, Avantika, Kasi, Puri, Kanchi and Dwarika are the seven sites which grant moksha. Though the city is linked mainly with the life of Lord Krishna, it is special even for Jains and Buddhists. Mathura’s holy ghats and serene banks of river Yamuna give a tranquil feel. Mathura holds strategic importance to India. It is the base of India’s strike corps I within Indian Army’s central command.

Mathura has had a rich heritage and has contributed richly to Indian culture. Mathura’s culture, its literature, songs, dance and cultural events revolve around the life of Lord Krishna. The culture of the people of Mathura is known as Braj culture. Various daily practices of the people of Mathura bring out the Braj culture Rasiya, a tradition of folk songs that describe the love of Radha and Lord Krishna is an integral part of Mathura’s culture and  of the festive celebration of Mathura. Mathura is known for Sanjhee, the art of decorating the ground with flowers. Raaslilas is a dance act that was performed by Lord Krishna along with gopis on banks of Yamuna River. Mathura museum is famous for the ancient sculptures of Mathura School of Art, it is an archeological museum.

One more aspect of Mathura that fascinates is how people from different nationalities, religion and race are getting painted with the colour of love of Shri Krishna. Mathura is truly a global city where people from various corners of the world come, lose themselves in the Krishna-divinity and start a new life in the ancient and narrow lanes of Mathura. You will find hundreds of ISKON (International Society of Krishna Consciousness) followers from foreign lands chanting Sanskrit mantras effortlessly.

Temple details

The basic structure of temples in India is a room or garbhagriha (sanctum sanctorum) where the image (murti) of the main Deity is kept. The temple is approached by a flight of steps and is often built on a platform. A porch covers the entrance to the temple, which is supported by carved pillars. A prominent roof called the shikhara surmounts the top of the garbhagriha, and dominates the surroundings. As time went by, small temples grew into temple complexes. Some temples have a hall (mandap) from where one can see the sanctum sanctorum.

Pothra Kund: This is a pond close to Janma Bhoomi. Vasudeva and Devaki used this pond for washing their clothes when they were in prison.

Sri Krishna Janma Bhoomi: This prison is the place where Lord Krishna was born to Sri Vasudeva and Yasodha Matha. There is a temple built at a later date. Inside we see Lord Krishna. There is a photograph of Lord Krishna here, which looks very much alive. The whole place is under security. There is a big hall in which we see huge sculptures of Lord Krishna and Radha. There are small sanctums for Durga, Navagraha etc. As we go around inside from a window we can see a huge wall of a mosque near the temple. Here they point to a place and say that was supposed to be the original place of jail.

Adi Varaha Swamy Temple: The place Mathura was known as Adi Varaha Kshetram. In Krutha Yuga, Kapila muni gave this idol of Adi Varaha to Lord Indra. Later Sathrugna brought this idol of Varaha from Ayodhya and installed it in Mathur

Swetha Varaha: Here Varaha is seen in white marble stone and known as Swetha Varaha Swami.

The present temple has been constructed in the 20th century. A stone slab marks the original spot of the birth of Lord Krishna. The earlier Kesava Deo temple had the room where Lord Krishna was born. The only dampener is the heavy security cordoning that has been done in this area. One has to go through complex and long security checks before getting entry into the complex. There is a dispute regarding a mosque that shares its wall with the temple.

Samyamana Ghat: This ghat is on the bank of River Yamuna. This is the ghat from where Vasudeva shifted Lord Krishna to Brindavan.

Visram Ghat: This is the ghat where Lord Krishna had a bath after Kamsa was killed and took rest.

The Twin Holy Cities

Mathura &amp; Vrindavan, the twin sacred towns of Hindu religion are situated in the state of Uttar Pradesh in India. Situated on the banksof the river Yamuna, both the places are closely and equally associated with religious sentiments of the people. Both Mathura and Vrindaban are believed to be the ancient birth places and playground of Lord Krishna.

Festivals

Holi : is celebrated on the full moon day in the month of Phalguna (Feb-March). Holi in Braja is celebrated for several days, at different places around Braja, before the actual day of Holi.

Basantha Panchami: the advent of spring is celebarted with folk and traditional flavour.

Maha Sivarathri: The divine birthplace of Lord Shri Krishna reverberated with the chants of Lord Shiva on the auspicious occasion of Mahashivaratri.

Janmashtami : the day when Lord Krishna was born is no wonder celebrated with much pomp and show. People enact the many legends during the time of Lord Krishna and folklore and recitals take place throughout the night.

Deepavali: On the day following Deepawali, Goverdhan pooja is celebrated when a splendid offering of chappan Bhog (56 variety of sweets and savories) is organized by the sansthan. The grand feast is offered at the Shri Giriraj Temple, Shri Radha Krishna Temple amid other temples at Janmasthan premise.

Sharad Purnima: Lord Shri Krishna had performed His Maharaas Leela on Sharad Purnima. Therefore, on Sharad Purnima – the auspicious full moon night, an elaborate Maharaas programme is organised at Shri Krishna Chabutra.

Goopashtami: On this day, Lord Keshavadeva is dressed up most beautifully in the attire of a cowherd. Using the soil, flowers, plants, tress and other articles from the Braja region, a forest-like scene is created in the Keshavadeva temple. On this day, worshipping and serving cows is considered to be auspicious.
</string>

<string name="kushal_bihari">
    King from Rajasthan who was very much devoted to Shri Barsana Dham made this temple. He decided to build the temple dedicated to Shri Laadli Laal. After completion of construction of the temple he also wanted to place the beautiful deity of Shri Laadli Laal currently residing in Shri Radharani temple, Barsana at the temple. He built small rooms around the deity where he and his family members, ministers could stay. When it was complete, a during the time of installation of deities, bringing the deities of the little temple to this place. But the day before the installation Shri Radharani appeared to the King in a dream and told him, “The place where the little temple is situated, that is my home, and not this.” Therefore, the King built another big temple where the little temple was. The King wasn’t angry or frustrated. He realized it as a grace of Shri Radharani. So Shri Radharani and Shri Krishn continue to reside where their place is. Albeli Sarkar Ki Jai.

Location:
Kushal Bihari temple, is near to Shri Radharani temple, half kilometer from Shri Radharani temple. When you go by car, you can place your car near to Kushal Bihari temple and can go by walking to Shri Radharani temple. Gehvar Van way also goes from other side of Kushal Bihari temple.
</string>

    <string name="man_ghar">
        The Man Mandir palace was built during the reign of Man Singh (1486-1516) and it is an excellent example of beautiful architecture. One important aspect of this palace is that it utilizes glazed tiles in different colours blue and brown to depict interesting designs along the interior as well as outside walls. Some of the figures depicted are ducks, elephants, peacocks, and lions. It has four storeys. Please carry a torch light with you because some of the steps are dark. Mughals captured this fort in 16th century and used it as prison. In the lower level rooms one can still see places where people were tortured. Guru Hargobind, the sixth guru of the Sikhs was prisoned here who when released also helped release some 50+ Rajas along with him. Keep the ticket purchased here because it would be required for other attractions in the Gwalior fort.
    </string>

<string name="Nandbaba">
    Krishna and his childhood pastimes amuse every pilgrim, and this amusement towards the supreme almighty brings the pilgrims to his own abode the Braj Dham. Every part of this region narrates a different character of Lord Krishna. From Mathura to Nandgaon-Barsana, the affiliation of Kanha’s childhood with these cities makes them a privileged destination of pilgrimage tours. Nandgaon is said to be the place where lord Kanha sort refuge from the cruelties of Kansa. Nand Bhavan in Braj is like revisiting the infancy of Lord Krishna. The opulence of Nand Bhawan can be judged by its sprawling vast complex. The premises are huge and few ascending stairs lead to its entrance. Nand Bhawan is wealthy in its manifestation. The wide open spaces around the palace bring the yester-world real to the eyes. There are fascinating rooms exclusively allotted to everyone including father Nand baba, mother Yashoda, mother Rohini, Shri Krishna, Baldev, Shri Radha and their allies. The residence is extensive as it had a kitchen, dining hall, restrooms, storerooms etc. The mythical place is wrapped up with stories from the spiritually significant era.
</string>

    <string name="Nidhivan">
        The Nidhivan temple houses a beautiful idol of Radha Krishna and is surrounded by a sacred ‘kunj’ or forest, where Lord Krishna and Radha rest after the ras leela is over. Nearby, there is a small temple called Rang Mahal where it is believed that Shri Krishna decorates Radha with his own hands. The temple also contains ornate beds for the deities to rest. Priests at Rang Mahal temple place toothbrushes, a saree, bangles, paan leaves, sweets and water before closing the gates after night aarti. However, everything is found scattered in the morning as if somebody has used them.
    </string>

    <string name="Pawan_Sarovar">
        Pavana means purifying and Sarovar means a lake. Thus, it’s believed that one who takes bath in Pavana Sarovar is relieved from all his sins. It is believed to be the place where Lord Krishna would bring his cows while returning from pastures in the evening. The cows would drink the cooling waters of Pavana Sarovar to quench their thirst. According to the legend, once Nand Raeji desired to go to Sangam Tirtha, Prayagraj in order to have sacred bath in the confluence of River Ganga, Yamuna and Saraswati. Unwilling to be separated from his parents, Krishna advised his foster father to travel the next day, on the auspicious occasion of Akshaya Tritiya. Next day, Nand Maharaj woke up early in the morning and when he went to Pavana Sarovar to have his morning bath, he saw a black complexioned person with a huge personality who seemed a stranger to him. Nand Maharaj enquired him about his identity. He told Nand Rae that he is the king of Tirthas Prayagraj and has come to wash of his sins in the sacred Pavana Sarovar which are left to him by pilgrims. He had come along with other rivers and Tirthas. Nand Maharaj was amazed to see that even the king of Tirthas, who washes of the sins of all pilgrims, has come to Pavana Sarovar to wash of his own sins leftover by the pilgrims. Thus, he admired the sanctity of the Pavana Sarovar and decided not to visit Prayag for bathing as the Prayagraj himself visits Pavana Sarovar for sacred bath to wash of the sins left by the pilgrims. Then, he had a bath in the holy waters of Pavana Sarovar and purified himself. On the northern bank of the Sarovar there is a temple by the name of Pavana-Bihari. It is believed to have been built at a place where Sri Radharani along with her sakhis (friends) would enjoy the water sports on the bank of the lake. Here on the bank of this lake Vrishabhanu, the father of Sri Radharani built a magnificent palace for her daughter.
    </string>

    <string name="Prem_mandir"> Prem Mandir is dedicated to Lord Rama and Lord Krishna. Prem Mandir is located in Vrindavan  holy city of district Mathura, Uttar Pradesh. The temple was established by Shri Kripalu Maharaj in January 2001 and it took almost 11 years  to complete. The temple was inaugurated on 17 February 2012 and was opened to public on 17th February itself.  Approximately 150 crores were spend on the expenditure of the temple. It is situated on a 54-acre site on the outskirts of Vrindavan, and is 125ft. high, 122ft. long, 115ft. wide. The temple will accommodate 25,000 people at a time and is still under construction. Italian marble is used in constructing the temple. The temple represents a renaissance in ancient Indian art and architecture. Ambiance of the temple is pious and spiritual. Lightening of the temple is used in a very modern way and within the intervals of 5-10 minutes it changes its color.  The temple beautifully describes the life of Lord Krishna. Govardhan Parvat and Kalia Naag, are the two most important events associated with his life that shows beautifully.
    </string>

    <string name="radha_rani">
        Radha Rani Temple which is a Hindu religious site. This temple is located in the Indian state of Uttar Pradesh Mathura Barsane. This temple is completely dedicated to Goddess Radha. This place is an important religious place for the devotees of Krishna. Radha Rani Temple is situated on a hill which is about 250 meters in height. Which is in the middle of the Barsana  so this hill is called the forehead of the Barsana. Radha Rani Temple is also called Barsane ki Ladli ka Mandir and Radha Rani Ka Mahal. This temple is about 400 years old. This temple was built by Raja Veer Singh in 1675 AD. Red and white stones have been used for the construction of the temple, which are considered to symbolize the love of Radha and Shri Krishna. The temple is reached by steps, which number about 108.

Radha Rani\'s father\'s name is Vrshabhanu and mother\'s name is Kirti. Radha Rani was born 15 days after Janmashtami on Ashtami of Shukla Paksha in the month of Bhadrapada. So for the people of Barsana, this place and day is very important. On this day the temple of Radha Rani is decorated with flowers. Radha Rani is offered Chhappan type dishes. The offerings of laddus in the temple are offered to Radha Rani. That Prasad is first fed with a peacock. Because peacock is considered to be the form of Radha-Shri Krishna. The prasad is later offered to the devotees.
In the Radha Rani temple, Shri Krishna Janmashtami and Radha Rani Janmashtami are especially celebrated with great pomp. Holi festival is special in Barsana, because Barsana Holi is famous all over the world. Lattmar Holi is played in Barsana, which started in the 16th century. During the festival days, the Barsana environment is very happy.
    </string>

<string name="Shri_rangji">
    Rangji Temple, situated on the Vrindavan - Mathura Marg, is dedicated to Lord Sri Goda Ranagamannar - a South Indian Vaishnava Saint and Lord Ranganatha - an incarnation of Lord Krishna. The highlight of the temple is the idol of Krishna present in the form of bridegroom with Goda (Andal) as his bride.

Goda, also known as Andal in South India, was a famous 8th century Vaishnava Saint known for composing "Tiruppuvai". It is a hymn for her beloved Lord Krishna and his birthplace Vrindavan. It is believed that seeing her dedication to him, Lord Krishna answered her prayers by agreeing to become her groom. This form of Krishna and Andal is idolized at the Rangji Mandir in Mathura-Vrindavan.

The unique temple is built in a South-Indian architectural style from the inside with a 50ft gold-plated dwajastambham (pillar) and a water tank, while the outsides of the temple are constructed following the North-India temple architecture. Rangji Mandir is also one of the 108 Divyadesams of the Vaishnavas.
</string>

    <string name="chitra_sakhee">
        oday is the divine appearance day of Chitra Sakhi. Chitra is the fourth of the varistha gopis. Her beautiful saffron complexion resembles the color of kumkuma, and her garments are the color of crystal. She is 26 days older than Srimati Radharani, being 14 years, 7 months and 14 days of age. Her father is Catura, the paternal uncle of Suryamitra. Her mother is Carcika-devi and her husband is Pithara. She is an adhika-mrdvinayika, and her home is in Chiksauli.
In gaura-lila she appears as Sri Govindananda. She and Sri Krsna are very affectionate toward each other, and she is very devoted to her seva of bringing cloves and garlands.She is especially expert in the lover’s quarrel between Radha and Krsna (the third of the six definitions of the word abhisarana). When Lord Madhava is full of bliss, she becomes satisfied.

Chitra-devi can read between the lines of books and letters written in many different languages, perceiving the hidden intentions of the author. She is a skilled gourmet and can understand the tastes of various foods made with honey, milk, and other ingredients simply by glancing at them. She can nicely make various kinds of nectarean beverages. (There are also eight other gopi maidservants, headed by Rasalika-devi, who are expert at making various nectarean beverages.) Chitra-devi is expert in playing music on pots filled with varying degrees of water. She is learned in the literature describing astronomy and astrology, and she is well versed in the theoretical and practical activities of protecting domestic animals. She is especially expert at gardening. There are other gopis who mostly collect transcendental herbs and medicinal creepers from the forest and do not collect flowers or anything else. Chitra-devi is the leader of these gopis. The chief gopis in Sri Chitra’s yutha are Rasalika, Tilakini, Saurasen, Sugandhika, Vamani, Vamanayana, Nagari and Nagavallika.

At Mayapur, Chitra Sakhi is adorned nicely with flowers &amp; garlands. Devotees offered Deep dan to Chitra Sakhi, praying for her mercy.

Sri Chitra Sakhi ki Jai!
    </string>
</resources>